{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Morgan Lewis defeated this man to become Governor of New York in 1804. James Wilkinson conspired with this man to create a monarchy in the American west with support from Spain. This man, Thomas Jefferson’s first Vice President, went to Weehauken, New Jersey to settle a personal dispute with a former Secretary of the Treasury. For ten points, name this man who killed Alexander Hamilton in an 1804 duel.",
      "answer": "Aaron Burr"
    },
    {
      "question": "ThisorganizationabsorbedMaktabal-KhidamatafterthedeathofAbdullahAzzaminacarbombing. A pair of attacks in Dar es Salaam and Nairobi on August 7, 1998, was orchestrated by this organization; those attacks on U.S. embassies prompted its leader to be placed on the FBI’s Most Wanted list. Khalid Sheikh Mohammed and Zacarias Moussaoui were members of this group until their arrest for planning and knowledge of another of this group’s attacks. For ten points, name this Islamic terrorist group that perpetrated the September 11th attacks under Osama bin Laden.",
      "answer": "al-Qaeda"
    },
    {
      "question": "Former President of Sears Julius Rosenwald was asked by this man to serve on the board of directors for an institute he headed. This man advised his people to “Cast down your bucket where you are” in his “Atlanta Compromise” speech, which was opposed by the formulator of the “Talented Tenth” doctrine, W.E.B. DuBois. For ten points, name this African-American leader of the Tuskegee Institute.",
      "answer": "Booker T. Washington"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man, who introduced the litmus test for differentiating acids and bases, used Robert Hooke’s air pump to refute contemporary claims that vacuums don’t exist. He coined the modern usage of the term “element” in 1661’s The Sceptical Chemist. For ten points, name this English scientist whose namesake gas law describes how, at constant temperature, the pressure and volume of a gas are inversely related.",
      "answer": "Robert Boyle"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Newcomen patented the first successful one of these devices, which was used to pump water out of mines. Hero of Alexandria’s aeliopile was a progenitor to this device, and John Smeaton created a competitor one of these products in England in the 1750s. Matthew Boulton worked to manufacture these devices with a man who installed a separate condenser to improve the efficiency of these devices. For ten points, name this invention, refined by James Watt, which provided power for the First Industrial Revolution in England.",
      "answer": "steam engine"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was arrested by Zhang Xueliang in the Xi’an Incident a year after his forces failed to capture an evading enemy on the Long March. This successor of Sun Yatsen was forced to settle at an island nation after losing a war against the Communist Party. For ten points, name this leader of the Kuomintang who escaped to Taiwan after losing the Chinese Civil War to Mao Zedong.",
      "answer": [
        "Chiang Kai-Shek",
        "Jiang Jieshi"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This player was selected one pick before David Greenwood after his team won a coin flip against the Chicago Bulls for the number one pick in the 1979 draft. In his final year at Michigan State, he defeated Larry Bird’s Indiana State in the NCAA championship game. This co-owner of the Dodgers started a foundation in 1991 to raise awareness of AIDS after he announced that he was HIV positive. For ten points, name this Hall of Fame point guard for the Los Angeles Lakers.",
      "answer": "Earvin “Magic” Johnson"
    },
    {
      "question": "In Florence, this commodity was produced by the Arte de Lana, and the Ciompi [CHOMP-ee] was an uprising of workers with this commodity. Production of this commodity was the cornerstone of the medieval English economy, where it drove the adoption of enclosure and was exported to the Flemish cloth trade. Eventually replaced in some part by Venetian-imported silk, for ten points, name this material, which one can obtain by shearing a sheep.",
      "answer": "wool"
    },
    {
      "question": "The goals of this agreement had been brought up earlier by John Slidell, and this treaty put an end to the war that began with the Thornton Affair. A failed clause in this treaty that would have outlawed slavery in the territories it acquired was known as the Wilmot Proviso, and the United States paid $15 million in this agreement to gain the lands north of the Rio Grande. For ten points, name this 1848 treaty that ended the Mexican-American War.",
      "answer": "Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city’s police operates a “black site” at Homan Square, where lawyers are not allowed to speak with clients. In October 2014, Jason Van Dyke, a member of this city’s police, shot Laquan McDonald 16 times; in November 2015, Van Dyke was charged with murder in Cook County. For ten points, name this Midwestern city where video of the McDonald shooting was released against the wishes of its mayor Rahm Emanuel.",
      "answer": "Chicago"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Hannibal’s War, also known as the Torstensson War, was a subsidiary of this larger conflict, which saw Christian IV of Denmark sign the Treaty of Lu¨beck after being defeated by Albrecht von Wallenstein. Frederick V was deposed after the Battle of White Mountain early in this war, which saw one side win the battle of Lu¨tzen despite the death of their king, who had earlier defeated Count Tilly at the Battle of Breitenfeld. Gustavus Adolphus died in, for ten points, what war, largely between Protestant and Catholic alliances?",
        "answer": "Thirty Years’ War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Thirty Years War was in part precipitated by what event, where two Austrian diplomats were thrown into a pile of horse manure in Bohemia?",
        "answer": "Second Defenestration of Prague"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Members of this class were often expected to master both the bun and the bu, and some of these people used weapons made by the 14th century steelsmith Masamune [mass-uh-moo-nay]. This class was replaced with a conscripted army following the Boshin War, which brought Emperor Meiji [may-jee] to power and ended the Tokugawa Shogunate. For ten points, name these medieval Japanese warriors.",
        "answer": "samurai accept, but do not otherwise reveal, bushi"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The name of this Shinto-inspired code of samurai chivalry translates to “way of the warrior.”",
        "answer": "bushido"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of these works ends with the phrase “Swell the mighty chorus to bring us nearer to victory!” Another of these works ended with the phase “together we cannot fail” and defended the creation of the FDIC. Harry Butcher coined the name for these works, which ended with the Star-Spangled Banner. “On Drought Conditions” and “On the Banking Crisis” were two of the 30 of, for ten points, what speeches delivered in a calm, familiar style over the radio to the American people from 1933 to 1944?",
        "answer": "Fireside chats"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The last fireside chat, given in June 1944, opened a sales drive for these governmental financial products.",
        "answer": "Series E war bonds"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One man who performed this action reached Chur after being defeated in the Battle of Zurich; that man was Alexander Suvorov. Charlemagne is one of three names inscribed at the bottom of a painting depicting this action, as well as that of one man who passed Publius Scipio while performing this action. That man used the Lesser Saint Bernard Pass to perform this action, and ended up losing lots of elephants. For ten points, name this common action, where Napoleon and Hannibal led armies over a certain mountain range.",
        "answer": "crossing the Alps"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napoleon was falsely depicted on a charger in Napoleon Crossing the Alps, which was painted by this French neoclassicist, who also painted the Oath of the Horatii.",
        "answer": "Jacques-Louis David"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Willaq-Umu served as these peoples’ spiritual leader, and oracles venerated by these people included one at Pachacamac. Three “pachas” represented the three realms of deities in these peoples’ religion. Inti was the sun god of these people, and he was venerated at Cusco, the capital of these peoples’ empire. For ten points, name this South American people, conquered by Francisco Pizarro and centered on modern-day Peru.",
        "answer": "Incans"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Incan religion believed that Inti was born on this lake, which contains the Isla del Sol and the Isla de la Luna. This lake straddles the border between Peru and Bolivia and is the largest lake by volume in South America.",
        "answer": "Lake Titicaca"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An 1856 law allowed the United States to claim Midway Atoll because it was a source of this commodity. The Haber-Bosch process for creating ammonia was invented when German access to caliche [ca-LEE-chay] and this commodity from the Peruvian and Chilean coasts was cut off in World War I. Nitrogen and other nutrients needed for fertilizers came from, for ten points, what valuable bat and seabird excrement?",
        "answer": "guano"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to nitrogen, guano is an exceptional source of this element, whose salts were once leached out from plant ashes. This was the first metal element isolated via electrolysis by Sir Humphrey Davy, shortly before his work with sodium.",
        "answer": "potassium or K"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Key insight into the cause of this event was provided by the Strubbe Tape. Glenn Frank prevented violent retaliation against the perpetrators off this event, which was sparked by opposition to the invasion of Cambodia. Mary Ann Vecchio’s screaming over Jeffrey Miller’s dead body was captured in an iconic photograph after, for ten points, what massacre of four students by the Ohio National Guard in 1970?",
        "answer": [
          "Kent State shootings or Kent State massacre",
          "equivalents"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Two days prior to the shooting, protesters set fire to a building for this military program, which trains officers at colleges and universities.",
        "answer": "Reserve Officers’ Training Corps or ROTC"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "At this city’s LEMD airport, Txeroki [”Cherokee”] used a van bomb to kill Carlos Palate. Another event in this city targeted four cercanias at its Atocha station and was wrongly blamed on the ETA by the outgoing Prime Minister, Jose Aznar, causing his party to lose his country’s general election. On March 11, 2004, Al-Qaeda bombed four trains in for ten points, what capital of Spain?",
        "answer": "Madrid"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The ETA terrorist group fights for the liberation of these people, who occupy an autonomous region in northern Spain.",
        "answer": "Basques"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Landslide Elections",
      "prompt": "Which U.S. President overwhelmingly defeated...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Alf Landon by a margin of 523-8, the best of his four Presidential victories?",
          "answer": [
            "Franklin Delano Roosevelt",
            "FDR"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "George McGovern in 1972?",
          "answer": "Richard Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "no one, winning unopposed in two unanimous Electoral College results?",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "no one, winning unopposed during the “Era of Good Feelings?”",
          "answer": "James Monroe"
        },
        {
          "question": "George McClellan, using the phrase “Don’t change horses in the middle of a stream?”",
          "answer": "Abraham Lincoln"
        },
        {
          "question": "Walter Mondale, who only carried Minnesota and D.C.?",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Adlai Stevenson, twice?",
          "answer": "Dwight Eisenhower"
        },
        {
          "question": "the author of The Conscience of a Conservative by 434 electoral votes?",
          "answer": [
            "Lyndon Baines Johnson",
            "LBJ"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Dynastic Houses",
      "prompt": "Which ruling house or dynasty...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "ended when Elizabeth I died childless?",
          "answer": "House of Tudor"
        },
        {
          "question": "was overthrown by Vladimir Lenin?",
          "answer": "House of Romanov"
        },
        {
          "question": "ruled Austria until 1918 and included Maria Theresa?",
          "answer": [
            "House of Habsburg",
            "House of Hapsburg"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "was replaced by the House of Valois after over three centuries of ruling France?",
          "answer": "House of Capet or Capetian dynasty"
        },
        {
          "question": "is the current ruling house of England?",
          "answer": "House of Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "ruled Portugal for almost 200 years and included Prince Henry the Navigator?",
          "answer": "House of Aviz"
        },
        {
          "question": "included Gustavus Adolphus and names a Swedish warship that sank minutes into her maiden voyage?",
          "answer": "House of Vasa"
        },
        {
          "question": "ruled Poland, but ended after the death of Casimir the Great?",
          "answer": "Piast Dynasty"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "1989",
      "prompt": "In 1989, who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "finished the second term of his U.S. presidency?",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "oversaw the fall of the Berlin Wall as leader of the Soviet Union?",
          "answer": "Mikhail Gorbachev"
        },
        {
          "question": "became the first African-American Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff?",
          "answer": "Colin Powell"
        },
        {
          "question": "became president of Czechoslovakia after the Velvet Revolution?",
          "answer": "Vaclav Havel"
        },
        {
          "question": "was the unnamed protestor captured on film blocking vehicles in Tiananmen Square?",
          "answer": "Tank Man"
        },
        {
          "question": "was the dictator of Panama overthrown by the U.S. in Operation Just Cause?",
          "answer": "Manuel Noriega"
        },
        {
          "question": "became the last Afrikaner President of South Africa to rule during Apartheid?",
          "answer": "Frederik Willem de Klerk"
        },
        {
          "question": "was re-buried in Budapest’s New Public Cemetery, 31 years after he was executed for withdrawing from the Warsaw Pact?",
          "answer": "Imre Nagy"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A king of this country formed the International African Association and sent Henry Morton Stanley to explore land for him. This country’s independence movement started after a riot at a performance of the (20 pts)",
        "opera The Mute Girl of Portici. This country signed the Treaty of London, which was dismissed as a “scrap of paper,” leading Britain to enter a war started by the (10 pts)",
        "assassination of Franz Ferdinand after this country’s neutrality was violated. For ten points, name this country that split from the Netherlands with capital at Brussels."
      ],
      "answer": "Belgium"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A joke about “two beautiful ladies” by the defendant fell flat during oral arguments in this case. Harry Blackmun consulted with the Mayo Clinic while writing his majority opinion in this case, whose petitioner, (20 pts)",
        "Norma McCorvey, later converted to Catholicism and began to oppose this decision. This case’s (10 pts)",
        "trimester framework was replaced in the 1992 Planned Parenthood v. Casey decision. For ten points, name this 1973 Supreme Court case which established that the right to privacy under the 14th Amendment covered a woman’s right to an abortion."
      ],
      "answer": "Roe v. Wade"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A man without this school of thought is described as a “dog tied to a cart” by its second leader, who worked as a water carrier at night. A crippled former-slave who taught this school had his works published by his pupil (20 pts)",
        "Arrian in the Discourses: that man was Epictetus. This movement’s later authors included an advisor to Nero, (10 pts)",
        "Seneca, and it was founded by Zeno of Citium in Athens around 300 BC. For ten points, name this Hellenistic philosophy which preached self-restraint and virtue."
      ],
      "answer": "Stoicism"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Gatun Lake was formed during the building of this structure, where William C. Gorgas worked to prevent the spread of yellow fever. Omar (20 pts)",
        "Torrijos negotiated a treaty with Jimmy Carter that transferred this structure to Torrijos’ nation in 1999. This structure, built between (10 pts)",
        "1907 and 1914, includes six locks and is crossed by the Bridge of the Americas. For ten points, name this artificial waterway in Central America that connects the Caribbean Sea to the Pacific Ocean."
      ],
      "answer": "Panama Canal"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This specific concept was described as the “heart of a heartless world” by one thinker. “They keep you doped with” this concept, “sex, and TV” according to John Lennon’s “Working Class Hero.” In 2008, (20 pts)",
        "Barack Obama explained that “it’s not surprising” that unemployed small-town people “get bitter” and “cling to (10 pts)",
        "guns or” this concept. For ten points, name this concept, described by Karl Marx as the “opium of the people,” whose varieties include Christianity."
      ],
      "answer": "religion"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One ruler of this empire supposedly had her husband Romanos III killed while taking a bath. That ruler was from this empire’s Macedonian dynasty whose namesake renaissance saw the creation of the (20 pts)",
        "Book of Ceremonies. That ruler, Empress Zoe, continued the veneration of (10 pts)",
        "icons, which reversed this empire’s earlier policy of Iconoclasm. For ten points, name this empire whose capital was Constantinople, and was formerly the Eastern Roman Empire."
      ],
      "answer": "Byzantine Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Thomas Jefferson advocated for this document, saying “half a loaf is better than no bread.” Barron v. Baltimore ruled that this document could not be applied to state governments; now, courts use the (20 pts)",
        "14th amendment to incorporate parts of this document to the states. One part of this document protects against cruel and (10 pts)",
        "unusual punishment, and its first section protects freedom of speech. For ten points, name this set of the first ten amendments to the U.S. Constitution."
      ],
      "answer": "Bill of Rights"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The novel Ice Candy Man centers around this historical event, and a novel awarded the “Booker of Bookers” revolves around the consequences of this event. Freedom at Midnight is a non-fiction work that describes the (20 pts)",
        "atrocities that occurred during this historical event, and children such as Shiva “of the Knees” and Parvati-the-witch have (10 pts)",
        "special powers because they were born during this event. For ten points, name this August 15, 1947 event that was chronicled by Salman Rushdie in Midnight’s Children in which two countries were created."
      ],
      "answer": "Partition of India"
    }
  ]
}